Okay
בוקר טוב. boker tov.
I hope everybody is staying warm and safe, although the snow doesn't
seem to be too bad here in New York, at least not
from where I sit. Anyway, we today's דף daf is דף ל"ז,
Daf Lamed Zayin, 37. We take up with the משנה Mishnah on
דף ל"ו עמוד ב', Daf Lamed Vav Amud Bet, so we're a
little behind, but this משנה Mishnah should sound very familiar. Hopefully it'll
go pretty quickly. Alright, so here we go. שבועת הפקדון, Shvuat Ha-Pikadon,
so at the beginning of a new פרק, perek, we move on
from the שבועת העדות Shvuat Ha-Edut about denying having it imposed upon
you,
possibly denying that you know testimony, maybe specifically denying in court that
you know testimony, to the שבועת הפקדון Shvuat Ha-Pikadon which is described
in the תורה Torah that you took the שבועה shvua yourself. It
actually calls it a מעילה, Me'ilah, מעל מעל בהשם, Ma'al Ma'al Bashem,
and the punishment or whatever, the consequence, is similar to מעילה. Me'ilah.
It is a קרבן korban and you pay a חומש. chomesh. It's
a קרבן אשם, korban asham, I should say, it's not an עולה
ויורד. oleh ve-yored.
But that's the שבועת הפקדון Shvuat Ha-Pikadon that you basically deny that
you have somebody's object in your, or some, that you owe something
to somebody, and you do it by invoking God's name. And the
interesting thing there is that it's described more than the other false
שבועות shvuot as a מעל בהשם, ma'al bashem, right, a trespass against
God. So that's interesting why it specifically uses the word מעילה Me'ilah
and frames it that way and has a קרבן korban similar to
the קרבן korban that you would bring for מעילה. Me'ilah. That is
a שבועת הפקדון. Shvuat Ha-Pikadon.
And it's not explicit there that if you have the שבועה shvua
imposed on you, that's what we learn from שבועת העדות. Shvuat Ha-Edut.
And now let's take a look at what the parameters are and
which ways it's similar and different to שבועת העדות. Shvuat Ha-Edut. So
the משנה Mishnah begins on דף ל"ו עמוד ב'. Daf Lamed Vav
Amud Bet. שבועת הפקדון Shvuat Ha-Pikadon נוהגת באנשים ובנשים, noheget be-anashim u-be-nashim,
it applies to men and to women because it's not about testimony,
so either one can take the oath. ברחוקים ובקרובים, be-rechokim u-be-krovim, whether
you're a relative or a non-relative. בכשרים ובפסולים, be-k'sherim u-be-psulim,
whether you're eligible to testify or not eligible to testify. בפני בית
דין ושלא בפני בית דין, bifnei beit din ve-shelo bifnei beit din,
whether in the presence of court or not, because שבועת העדות, Shvuat
Ha-Edut, according to some, the denial had to be specifically in the
presence of the court.
מפי עצמו, mipi atzmo, on your own, that's in the תורה, Torah,
it sounds like you yourself volunteer the שבועה. shvua. ומפי אחרים, u-mipi
acherim, now from other people imposing the שבועה shvua on you, which
is something we learn out from
שבועת העדות. Shvuat Ha-Edut.
ומפי אחרים חייב שיכפרו
בבית דין.
u-mipi acherim chayav
she-yichperu be-beit din. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That is only
if you deny in בית דין beit din because since you learn
it from שבועת העדות, Shvuat Ha-Edut, he says דון מינה ומינה, don
mina u-mina, that you learn it with its original context. So the
same way in שבועת העדות Shvuat Ha-Edut it's only when the denial
is in בית דין, beit din, here too, where you do it
on your own, it would be even outside of בית דין, beit
din, but when it's imposed on you, which we learn from שבועת
העדות, Shvuat Ha-Edut, it's only in the presence, it's only if you're
rejecting it and you're denying it. Somebody says משביע אני עליכם mashpia
ani aleichem that you don't have, you know, my money, and you
say I don't have your money. You don't have to say אמן,
amen, because if you said אמן, amen, then that's מפי עצמו. mipi
atzmo. That would apply even outside of בית דין. beit din. So
the real מושבע מפי אחרים mushba mipi acherim is when you don't
say אמן, amen, but you just assert, you say I don't know
testimony, in this case, I don't have your object. Okay, so רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that's only
בפני בית דין. bifnei beit din. וחכמים אומרים, ve-chachamim omrim, and the
וחכמים chachamim say, בין מפי עצמו בין מפי אחרים, bein mipi atzmo
bein mipi acherim, כיון שכפר בו חייב, kevan she-kafra bo chayav, whether
done by yourself or imposed by others, once you deny it, it
does not have to be in the presence of בית דין. beit
din. דון מינה ואוקמה באתרה. don mina ve-okimeh be-asrah. Yes, we learn
other people imposing it from שבועת העדות, Shvuat Ha-Edut, but we apply
it to this context and it does not require
בית דין. beit din. כיון שכפר בו חייב. kevan she-kafra bo chayav.
Now, so that's that debate, which parallels or is the mirror image
of a debate we had by שבועת העדות. Shvuat Ha-Edut. וחייב על
זדון השבועה ועל שגגתה עם זדון הפקדון. ve-chayav al zadon ha-shvua ve-al
shegagatah im zadon ha-pikadon. Okay, this is similar to now שבועת העדות,
Shvuat Ha-Edut, whether you are willfully, intentionally doing it, even if you're
מזיד, mezid,
or if you are a שוגג shogeg but you are זדון הפקדון.
zadon ha-pikadon. You are willfully lying, because again, if you are forgetting
or whatever, that's an אונס, oness, you're not even חייב chayav for
a false שבועה. shvua. So you have to, so in either case
you have to willfully lie, but you could either be a מזיד
mezid about knowing that you're going to have to bring a קרבן
korban or שוגג shogeg not knowing you'll have to bring a
קרבן. korban. Doesn't seem to be too big of a difference. But
you do have to be willfully lying. ואינו חייב על שגגתה גרידתא.
ve-eino chayav al shegagatah gretata. And you're not חייב chayav on just
a straight שגגה. shegagah. A straight שגגה shegagah could either be referring
to the case where you think you're telling the truth, of course
that's not a שוגג, shogeg, that's considered an אונס. oness. Or maybe
it's talking about you don't realize that there's any איסור issur in
the תורה Torah to lie through a שבועה. shvua. You must be
pretty oblivious to that. morality as well, but you don't realize that
there's any prohibition. Actually no, that is, yeah, excuse me, that's the
case. שוגג shogeg is that you don't realize that there is any...
let me just check
רש״י Rashi here. No, רש״י Rashi says the first one, that you
think you're telling the truth, although there's a question is that would
be called an אונס, oness, a שוגג shogeg because it's really an
אונס, oness, רש״י Rashi himself says it's an אונס. oness. Or, yup,
other possibility is you know you're lying, but you think it's totally
מותר. muttar. Not only do you think you don't bring a קרבן,
korban, you actually think it's totally מותר, muttar, which is a pretty
shocking possibility. Anyway, with so it's a pure שוגג, shogeg, one of
those two variations, you do not bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, ומה
חייב על זדונה, u'ma chayav al zidona, what do you bring when
you are willful, willfully lying, whether you do or don't know you'll
have to bring a קרבן, korban, but you're certainly willfully lying and
you know you're violating. Okay, ומה חייב על זדונה? u'ma chayav al
zidona? אשם בכסף שקלים. asham b'kesef shkalim.
You don't bring an עולה ויורד, olah v'yored, a variable cost קרבן,
korban, meaning variable cost because it could be an animal or birds
or מנחה mincha depending on your wealth. No, this is an אשם,
asham, everybody brings an animal, an אשם, asham, male, you know, sheep
or whatever, goat or something. And בכסף שקלים, b'kesef shkalim, it would
have to cost two שקל, shekel, which is a non-trivial minimum amount.
And we learn that out from אשם מעילות, asham me'ilot, we make
we learn that from there we learn all our other אשמים. ashamim.
Okay, so that's what you bring. שבועת הפקדון כיצד? shvuat hapikadon keitzad?
Now this, as you see, the entire פרקים, perakim, all the משניות
mishnayos of the פרק perek are all here joined into one because
it's such a short פרק. perek. So that's the basic parameters, ways
in which it's similar, ways in which it's different to שבועת עדות.
shvuat eidus. Now, שבועת הפקדון כיצד? shvuat hapikadon keitzad? What's the scenario,
שבועת
הפקדון? shvuat hapikadon? אמר
לו, amar lo, תן לי פקדון שהפקדתי בידך. tein li pikadon she-hifkadeti
b'yadecha.
Give me my object I gave you for safekeeping, excuse
me. שבועה שאין לך בידי. shvuah she-ein l'cha b'yadi.
No, I take an oath you don't have it, that's מפי עצמו.
mipi atzmo. או שאמר לו, o she-amar lo, אין לך בידי, ein
l'cha b'yadi,
or he just says I don't have that object. משביע אני, mashpia
ani, he says take a שבועה, shvuah, ואמר אמן. v'amar amen. Yes,
I accept the שבועה, shvuah, or I impose a שבועה shvuah on
you. אמן. amen. So אמן amen is also מושבע מפי עצמו, mushba
mipi atzmo, the אמן amen is like you said it yourself. הרי
זה חייב. harei zeh chayav. That you're חייב. chayav. Now
the question about מושבע מפי אחרים, mushba mipi acherim, if he said
משביע אני עליכם mashpia ani aleichem or עליך alecha and he said
I don't have it. I don't know what you're talking about, I
don't have it. So you don't say אמן, amen, that still is
also חייב, chayav, but that's a debate of where that has to
take place. Okay, now we get to the issue about being able
to bring multiple ones because of the way it's phrased. השביע עליו
חמש פעמים, hishpia alav chamesh pe'amim,
or the number of times he did it. Five times the guy
said משביע אני עליך, mashpia ani alecha, משביע אני עליך. mashpia ani
alecha. בין בפני בית דין ובין שלא בפני בית דין, bein bifnei
beit din u'bein she-lo bifnei beit din, whether in the presence of
a בית דין beit din or not, וכפר, v'kafar, and he denied
it. So this would be the חכמים chachamim that even if you
don't say אמן, amen, you just deny it, which is מושבע מפי
אחרים, mushba mipi acherim, you're חייב chayav even outside of בית דין.
beit din. חייב, chayav, so number one, that's the scenario where the
חכמים chachamim and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir debate. But more importantly for
our purposes, חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achat v'achat.
You're חייב chayav for each individual one since there were five acts
of imposing the שבועה shvuah on you. Presumably even if you didn't
say אמן amen or deny each one, you only denied it once.
אמר רבי שמעון מה טעם? amar Rabbi Shimon ma ta'am? What's the
reason that you're חייב chayav multiple times? מפני שיכול לחזור ולהודות. mifnei
she-yachol lachzor u'l'hodot. Because you could go back and admit. Right, this
is contrasted to the case
of שבועת עדות shvuat eidus where שבועת עדות shvuat eidus if it's
five times in the presence of בית דין beit din you only
bring one קרבן. korban. Because once there's one denial, then the other
cases are, since כיון שהעיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד. keivan she-he'id shuv
eino chozer u'magid. You can't go back and do it another time.
So in front of בית דין beit din it's only חייב chayav
once. Here, outside of בית דין beit din you're חייב chayav five
times, even if it's מפי אחרים, mipi acherim, that's the חכמים chachamim
against רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And in the presence of בית דין
beit din you're also חייב chayav five times because even after you've
denied it in בית דין, beit din, you're not here the עד,
ed, you're here a נטען ונטען, nito'an v'nitan, a litigant, so even
after your first denial, you can go back and admit. So that's
why here you're חייב chayav five times even in the presence of
בית דין beit din in contrast to שבועת עדות. shvuat eidus. Okay.
Now היו חמשה תובעים אותו. hayu chamishah tvu'im oto. Five different people
were demanding an object from you. אמרו לו, amru lo, and they
said to him, תן לנו פקדון שיש לנו בידך. tein lanu pikadon
she-yesh lanu b'yadecha. And these five people really are a consortium, it's
not five different claims, that would be obvious. But these five people
are a consortium and they all say look, we all entrusted to
you this one object that we own in partnership, we entrusted it
to you for safekeeping. And he says, בשבועה
שאין לכם. b'shvuah she-ein lachem. בידי. beyadi. No, I take an oath,
you don't have it. אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino chayav ela achas.
In that case, since it's only one שבועה shvua and one demand,
it's only one קרבן. korban. Now, let's say he responds in a
slightly different way. It's still one ownership, it's a partnership ownership, they're
all coming at the same time. But the way he responds is
by identifying each separate owner. לא לך ולא לך ולא לך. lo
lecha v'lo lecha v'lo lecha. You don't and you don't and you
don't. In that case, חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol
achas v'achas. Since he pointed out and identified each owner, he's חייב
chayav for a separate שבועה shvua for each one. רבי שמעון אומר
עד שיאמר שבועה באחרונה. Rabbi Shimon omer ad sheyomar shvua b'achrona. No,
no, no. That's... I'm not going to consider those separate שבועות shvuos
as we had a discussion earlier when you identified an object. But
here
it's a consortium that owns this product. I'm not going to separate
that as defined as different שבועות, shvuos, unless you say the word
שבועה shvua at the end. שבועה shvua that I don't have, that
I don't have the פיקדון pikadon of yours, your פיקדון pikadon or
you know yours or yours or yours or yours, שבועה. shvua. If
you say שבועה shvua at the end, then that means that you
want to identify each separate person as a separate שבועה. shvua. Or
whether you want to or not, that's halachically how it'll be defined.
Okay. תני לי פיקדון ותשומת יד וגזל ואבידה שיש לי בידך. Tni
li pikadon u’tesumes yad v’gazel va’aveida sheyesh li b’yadecha. Okay, now here's
different objects, so identify different objects. So what is it? They're different
ways in which you got the object. Give me back the object
I gave you for safekeeping and the stuff you stole from me
and you know and what's the other one and my אבידה aveida
that you found that you're denying. Okay. So you have multiple things
of mine and you got them all through different ways. Okay. And
I say give them back to me. And you say שבועה שאין
לך בידי. shvua she’ein lecha b’yadi. You just say a simple שבועה,
shvua, I don't have anything of yours. אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino
chayav ela achas. That we can all agree is only one שבועה
shvua and one קרבן. korban. שבועה שאין לך בידי פיקדון ותשומת יד
וגזל ואבידה. shvua she’ein lecha b’yadi pikadon u’tesumes yad v’gazel va’aveida. If
however the guy says a שבועה shvua I don't have of yours,
neither פיקדון pikadon nor a תשומת יד, tesumes yad, which is whatever,
we'll go back to what that means now, let's say I've you
know I've been שלח יד בפיקדון shaloch yad b’pikadon or something of
that nature, I've taken use of your object I shouldn't have, or
I didn't steal anything and I didn't find an object that I
didn't return. In all those cases, so basically I take one שבועה
shvua but I mention specifically the five different ways that you're demanding
five different objects from me. חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al
kol achas v’achas. There you bring a separate קרבן korban and there
even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you don't have to say the
word שבועה shvua at the end because that's not a שותפות shutfus
and it's all really one claim of one object. In this claim,
yes, it's one litigant, but it's five different types of objects, five
different debts he's demanding from me. If I identify each object and
each debt separately, even without the word שבועה shvua at the end,
that's five שבועות. shvuos. Now, תני לי חטים ושעורים וכוסמין שיש לי
בידך. Tni li chitin u’seorin v’chusmin sheyesh li b’yadecha.
Let's say it's really one, you know, a transaction, but it's five
different physical objects. In one transaction I gave you a bag that
had in it wheat and barley and spelt. And I say give
me the wheat and barley and spelt. So the guy says שבועה
שאין לך בידי. shvua she’ein lecha b’yadi. He takes the שבועה. shvua.
אינו חייב אלא אחת. Eino chayav ela achas. So if it's only
he just refers to it as one thing, only one קרבן. korban.
But if he says שבועה שאין לך בידי חטים ושעורים וכוסמין, shvua
she’ein lecha b’yadi chitin u’seorin v’chusmin, חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
chayav al
kol achas v’achas. Okay. If he says however he identifies the objects,
I don't have wheat, spelt or barley, even though it's one litigant
and one transaction, if they're identified, then חייב, chayav, then you bring
separate קרבנות. korbanos. So we all agree if the objects are somehow
singled out, either because they are different physical objects, different types of
objects, wheat, spelt or barley, or they're really different transactions, then everybody
agrees you bring a separate קרבן korban even without saying the word
שבועה shvua at the end. The only debate earlier was when it
was five people coming and demanding from me one object that they
as five people entrusted to me. And if I identify different litigants,
that was the debate of whether I need to say the word
שבועה shvua to bring a separate קרבן. korban. Okay. רבי מאיר אומר
אפילו אמר חטים ושעורים וכוסמין. Rabbi Meir omer afilu amar chitin u’seorin
v’chusmin. Even if he does say חטים, chitin, right, wheat, you know,
barleys, we don't have an exact parallel in English, but just the
one wheat, one barley, you don't have even one wheat in my
hand, one barley, one you know one piece of spelt, חייב. chayav.
So what's that really debating is not clear. חייב על כל אחת
ואחת. chayav al kol achas v’achas. Okay. חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
chayav al kol achas v’achas. Now, you should be noticing that this
is all very parallel to what we saw by שבועת העדות. shvuas
eidus. So now let's talk about what type of way that this
guy might have a debt to me.
If the person says אנסת ופתית את בתי, anasta u’fitita es biti,
you raped or seduced my daughter, והוא אומר לא אנסתי ולא פתיתי,
v’hu omer lo anasti v’lo fititi, I did not, משביע אני ואמר
אמן, mashpiah ani v’amar amen, חייב. chayav. You're חייב. chayav. Okay, why?
Because...
well let's take a look what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. רבי
שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts. שאינו משלם
קנס על פי עצמו. she’eino m’shalem knas al pi atzmo. Because he
says fundamentally normally we think... Take a look at what רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says. רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon exempts, שאינו משלם קנס על פי עצמו, she-eino meshallem k’nas al
pi atzmo, because he says normally we think about that as a
scenario where the guy pays a קנס k’nas of fifty shekel in
the תורה. Torah. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, look, you’re not
asking עדים, edim, you’re asking this guy. So let’s say the guy
admitted what you wanted him to admit. He wouldn't have to pay
you. He's a מודה בקנס. modeh b'k'nas. So by denying something that
even had he admitted he would be exempt, he doesn't
have—there's no reason that the lying should be like an act of
stealing from you, because even if he would admit he would be
exempt.
So אמרו לו, amru lo, so that seems a pretty reasonable argument.
So they said back to him, אף על פי שאינו משלם קנס
על פי עצמו משלם בושת ופגם על פי עצמו. af al pi
she-eino meshallem k’nas al pi atzmo meshallem boshet u-pegam al pi atzmo.
The claim, אנסת ופתית את בתי, anasta u-pitita et biti, that's not
just a claim that's demanding for the payment of קנס. k’nas.
That's a debate that is within that is also the other debts
that that has. The actual injury, the embarrassment, the shame, the suffering,
and so on. So because those are part of the same demand,
therefore it's a demand of ממון, mamon, not just a demand of
קנס. k’nas. And if you did admit you would be חייב chayav
for those aspects of it. So that's a very good response, that's
what the חכמים Chachamim would say. Okay, and so now we go
on.
גנבת את שורי, ganavta et shori, you stole my ox, והוא אומר
לא גנבתי, v’hu omer lo ganavti, I didn't. משביעך אני ואמר אמן
חייב, mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Well, that's obvious.
גנבתי אבל לא טבחתי ולא מכרתי. ganavti aval lo tavachti v’lo macharti.
Let's say I said you stole my ox and you slaughtered it
or you sold it and you have to pay for
four times the
amount,
excuse me, five times the amount.
והוא
אומר לא גנבתי. v’hu omer lo ganavti. משביעך אני ואמר אמן פטור,
mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen patur, you're פטור. patur. Why? Because so he
admits, he says גנבתי, ganavti, I did steal it but I didn't
do the other thing. If he said I didn't steal it or
I didn't even steal it let alone sell it or slaughter it,
right,
then we could have that debate. Are you talking because a major
part of what I'm demanding is the קנס, k’nas, but there's an
element of it which is the ממון, mamon, which is the basic
payment of the ox itself. So that would have paralleled the earlier
debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים. Chachamim. Are you
פטור patur because fundamentally we say it's about the קנס k’nas or
are you חייב chayav because there's also the principle? But if the
guy says I admit that I stole it, but I didn't do
the other thing, and I don't have to pay the four and
five, but I do have to pay the principle, so then the
only thing we're debating is the קנס. k’nas. If the only thing
we're debating is קנס, k’nas, everybody agrees he's exempt because even if
he would admit it he would be exempt. Okay, so in that
case,
גנבתי, ganavti, so it says, I'm sorry, so he says, גנבתי אבל
לא טבחתי ולא מכרתי משביעך אני ואמר אמן פטור. ganavti aval lo
tavachti v’lo macharti mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen patur. In that case, everybody
agrees you're פטור patur because it's all about the קנס. k’nas. המית
שורך את שורי, hemit shorcha et shori, your ox killed my ox.
והוא אומר לא המית, v’hu omer lo hemit, I didn't. משביעך אני
ואמר אמן חייב. mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen chayav. In that case, you're
חייב chayav because then it's all about ממון. mamon. But if he
says, המית שורך את עבדי, hemit shorcha et avdi, your ox killed
my slave, and that's a fixed thirty shekel which is a קנס.
k’nas. והוא אומר לא המית, v’hu omer lo hemit, I didn't. משביעך
אני ואמר אמן פטור. mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen patur. Then he's exempt
because even if he were to admit it would be a קנס
k’nas and he'd be exempt. אמר לו, amar lo,
חבלת בי, chavalta bi, you wounded me, ועשית בי חבורה, v’asita bi
chavura, and you made a wound. והוא אומר לא חבלתי ולא עשיתי
בך חבורה, v’hu omer lo chavalti v’lo asiti becha chavura, I didn't.
משביעך אני ואמר אמן חייב. mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen chayav. In that
case, you're חייב chayav because making a wound there are ממון mamon
payments. Maybe some of those payments are treated as קנס, k’nas, but
certainly a lot of them are treated as ממון, mamon, as basic
compensation, and therefore if you would admit you'd be חייב. chayav. So
if you deny with a שבועה shvuah you're
חייב. chayav. אמר לו עבדו, amar lo avdo, but if your slave
says to you,
הפלת את שיני וסימית את עיני, hipalta et shini v’simita et eini,
you knocked out my tooth or my eye, and the result would
be that the slave would go free, and that's considered to be
a קנס k’nas because even though it's obviously
a type of a compensation for the fact that he was injured,
but nevertheless
it's the
same—it's a
flat—it's not proportional to the injury. The punishment is always the same
or the compensation is always the same, that the slave goes free.
So that's seen as a type of a קנס. k’nas. והוא אומר
לא הפלתי ולא סימיתי, v’hu omer lo hipalti v’lo simiti, I did
not do that. משביעך אני ואמר אמן פטור, mashbi’acha ani v’amar amen
patur, then he'd be exempt, because the only thing they're debating is
a קנס, k’nas, and if he would admit it he would also
be exempt. זה הכלל כל המשלם על פי עצמו חייב ושאינו משלם
על פי עצמו פטור. ze ha-klal kol ha-meshallem al pi atzmo chayav
v’she-eino meshallem al pi atzmo patur. Anything that were you to admit
you would have to pay and your denying, then you bring a
קרבן. korban. If were you to admit you'd be exempt, then in
your denial you're not
really keeping money away from this person. In that case, you are
exempt from a קרבן korban and the debate was, let's say the
claim. contains both elements, in that case are we going to treat
it as קנס knas or are we going to treat it as
ממון? mamon? Okay fine, that is the משנה. mishna. Now we start
with the גמרא. Gemara. רב אחא בר הונא, Rav Acha bar Huna,
רב שמואל ברי דרבה בר בר חנה, Rav Shmuel brei deRabbah bar
bar Chana, רב יצחק ברי דרב הונא, Rav Yitzchak brei deRav Huna,
so these three rabbis, two of them seem to have been brothers,
הוו תנו שמעתתא בי רבה, havay tanu shematata bei Rabbah, they were
learning שבועות Shvuos in the house of Rabbah. You might remember an
earlier case where somebody was learning, you know, a case of an
earlier פרק perek of שבועות Shvuos and his brother met up with
him and asked him these questions and sort of, you know, trips
him up. So it's not exactly going to be the same here,
but anyway, they were all learning שבועות Shvuos in the ישיבה yeshiva
of Rabbah. פגע בהו רב כהנא, paga behu Rav Kahana, so רב
כהנא Rav Kahana
אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, oh you're learning שבועות?
Shvuos? I've got some questions, maybe you can answer me.
So
אמר להו, amar lehu, מזיד בשבועת הפקדון והתרו בו מהו? mazid bishvuat
hapikadon vehitru bo mahu? Let's say, this is a question I think
we've all been waiting to ask,
let's say somebody is מזיד mazid with שבועת הפקדון, shvuat hapikadon, because
the classic case of שבועת הפקדון shvuat hapikadon and all these שבועות
shvuos is that he's מזיד, mazid, right? And
and they actually gave him התראה, hatra'ah, they actually gave him warning,
and they said we know you're lying, we know these witnesses said
this, we know you've actually got that object in your house,
and if you swear falsely, you
will have to get lashes because you transgress taking a false oath,
or at least that's what they said, that you'll get lashes. That
is going to be the question. Will they indeed get lashes? Is
there actually lashes in these cases of false oaths, which we've been
saying even in מזיד mazid scenarios you'll bring a קורבן? korban? So
how much are we saying that מזיד mazid is just about קורבן,
korban, or is that just if they're not going to get lashes,
but if they're warned about lashes, maybe you genuinely, you know, will
get lashes. So that's the question. Okay, so והתרו בו מהו, vehitru
bo mahu, and they gave him warning,
what's the הלכה? halacha? Do we say כיון דחידוש הוא דבכל התורה
לא אשכחן מזיד דמייתי קורבן, keivan dechidushu hu debichol hatorah lo ashkenan
mazid demaytei korban, since this whole thing is a חידוש, chidush, that
in the whole תורה Torah we never find a מזיד mazid brings
a קורבן. korban. Now it's not really true. רש״י Rashi gives four
examples that a מזיד mazid brings a קורבן. korban. But okay, the
point is not that it's unique from all other cases in the
תורה, Torah, but the point is since מזיד mazid brings a קורבן,
korban, maybe that's the only thing that you do for מזיד mazid
here.
והכא מייתי קורבן, vehacha maytei korban, so here you bring a קורבן,
korban, לא שנא אתרו ביה ולא שנא לא אתרו ביה, lo shna
itru bei velo shna lo itru bei, it doesn't matter if they
gave him warning or not, the only punishment the תורה Torah assigns
to this guy is a קורבן korban even with witnesses. That's one
possibility. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say הני מילי היכא
דלא אתרו ביה, hanei milei heicha de lo itru bei, the קורבן
korban is only when there's not warning for lashes, אבל היכא דאתרו
ביה, aval heicha de itru bei, if they warn him for lashes,
מלקי לקי קורבן לא מייתי, malki laky korban lo maytei, so then
he does get lashes and he doesn't bring a קורבן. korban. So
there's one, so here's two possibilities. One is you bring a קורבן
korban even with warning, the other is with warning you get lashes
and no קורבן. korban. And of course there's a third possibility: with
warning you get both.
או דילמא הא והא עבדינן, o dilma ha veha avdinan, we'll do
both. אמרו ליה, amru lei, so they said to רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, תנינא, tanina, we taught it, חמורה הימנה שבועת הפקדון, chamura himena
shvuat hapikadon, we have a ברייתא braita that teaches that שבועת הפקדון
shvuat hapikadon is more weighty than שבועת העדות. shvuat ha'eidus.
In what way is it more weighty than שבועת העדות? shvuat ha'eidus?
חמורה הימנה שבועת הפקדון שחייבין על זדונה מלקות ועל שגגתה אשם בכסף
שקלים, chamura himena shvuat hapikadon shechayavin al zedonah malkot ve'al shigegatah asham
bekesef shekalim, that if you do it willfully
you get lashes, and if you do it בשוגג beshogeig another way
it's more weighty is it's not a קורבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh
veyored, that it depends how big of a קורבן korban you bring
based on how wealthy you are, it's always the same expensive קורבן
korban of an אשם asham worth two שקלים. shekalim. Okay, so that's
two ways in which it is weightier. But what we're going to
focus on is it said מזיד mazid you get lashes. So that's
pretty darn explicit, that for מזיד mazid you get lashes. The only
question is, do you get lashes and a קורבן korban or only
lashes? But the פשט pshat it sounds like only lashes. So that
seems to answer the question. Now, the other question is, why is
this only true
by שבועת הפקדון? shvuat hapikadon? Once this is true let it be
true by שבועת העדות shvuat ha'eidus as well, that if you get
warning you should get lashes.
So רש״י Rashi says
because we don't know that you're lying
and therefore we'll never be able to give you lashes because how
do we know that you actually saw it? Of course, and רש״י
Rashi calls it התראת ספק. hatra'at safek. So תוספות Tosafot says that's
not התראת ספק hatra'at safek because the person himself knows if he's
lying. Okay, but you could still say we can't prove it. But
that's not exactly true either, like we don't know if you saw
it. Maybe I did, maybe I saw you seeing something else, I
mean maybe there would be a case of two sets of witnesses,
but whatever, but it's not really impossible for me to know that
you were a witness to something. So why wouldn't this apply to
שבועת העדות? shvuat ha'eidus? So תוספות Tosafot says a different reason, because
שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'eidus, since I'm asking you to testify about what
you remember, maybe you say you don't know it and you really
forgot, maybe you are really thinking yes I saw
you I
know. but that’s a little bit different, because there you could imagine
a scenario that the guy
actually has it in his pocket, somehow it’s a context which it’s
clear that he knows that it’s the guy’s thing. The iPhone says
on it John’s iPhone. Anyway, it’s still not clear though, for as
you could still say that moment I took the שבועה, Shvua, I
forgot. Let’s say I testified I saw something a minute ago and
now you’re asking me to testify about it. I was witness to
a car crash, and you’re asking me, and I was there and
I got out of my car and I saw it or whatever,
and then you’re asking me to put a שבועה Shvua on me
that I should come and testify. Anyway, so it’s not a hundred
percent clear why this does not apply by שבועת עדות Shvuat Edot
as well, but one way or another, we’re saying that this is
a case where to know that the guy knows it and to
be able to prove it is more clear in the case of
שבועת פיקדון. Shvuat Pikadon. So anyway, so that’s the way שבועת פיקדון
Shvuat Pikadon is weightier than שבועת עדות Shvuat Edot is that you
would get lashes. So that’s a clear answer, that if you’re warned,
you get lashes. So it says, מכדי קאמר mikdi ka'amar
and presumably only lashes, מדקאמר ליה mid'ka'amar lei אזידו מלקות azido malkot
for willful you get מלקות, malkot, מכלל דאזהורי, miklal d'azhorei,
the only scenario is you get warning, דקאמר d'ka'amar מלקות malkot אין
in and it’s presumably saying only מלקות, malkot, קרבן לא korban lo
and not a קרבן. korban. Now if it’s only מלקות malkot and
not a קרבן, korban, why is that weightier than for example שבועת
עדות Shvuat Edot which would bring a קרבן? korban? So the answer
is obvious. ומאי חומרא, U'mai chumra, why is since it’s only one,
it’s not two, why is that what’s the weightiness of מלקות? malkot?
דניחא ליה לאיניש דמייתי קרבן ולא לילקי. Danicha lei l'inish d'maiti korban
v'lo lilki. That’s pretty obvious, I’d much rather bring the קרבן korban
than get lashes. Okay, so there you go, that’s your full answer.
Yes, you get lashes and it’s only lashes. אמר להו רבא בר
איסו. Amar lehu Rava bar Isu. So רבא בר איסו Rava bar
Isu said to this group who they thought that they had an
answer to רב כהנא’s Rav Kahana question, מן תנא זדון שבועת פיקדון
לא ניתן לכפרה ר' שמעון. Man tanna zadon shvuat pikadon lo nitan
l'khapara Rabbi Shimon. No, no, no, no, you can’t prove that this
is דברי הכל. divrei hakol. You might remember that a day or
two ago, we learned ר' שמעון Rabbi Shimon who basically says that
since it says ומעלה מעל בה' u'ma'ala ma'al b'Hashem by שבועת
פיקדון, shvuat pikadon, that שבועת פיקדון shvuat pikadon
if you’re מזיד, mezid, you actually do not bring a קרבן. korban.
The only קרבן korban is like מעילה Me'ilah when it’s בשוגג. b'shogeg.
You would still have to know you’re lying, but you’re שוגג shogeg
about the קרבן. korban. But anyway, the only case of שבועת פיקדון
shvuat pikadon is only שוגג, shogeg, not מזיד. mezid. So that according
to him,
if you’re מזיד mezid you’ll get lashes, because he doesn’t have the
whole idea of קרבן korban doesn't if you’re מזיד mezid with warning
you get lashes, because he never has the קרבן korban by any
scenario of מזיד. mezid.
That’s so that ברייתא braita we’ll say is going according to him.
That doesn’t answer for us what would be the story if you
were the if you bring a קרבן במזיד korban b'mezid when you
don’t get warning,
then we want to know what happens when you do get warning.
Okay, so he says מן תנא זדון שבועת פיקדון לא ניתן לכפרה.
man tanna zadon shvuat pikadon lo nitan l'khapara. The author of that
ברייתא braita that there’s no קרבן korban by שבועת פיקדון, shvuat pikadon,
that’s ר' שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that’s ר' שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So for
him of course if there’s warning there’s lashes. He doesn’t have a
קרבן במזיד korban b'mezid altogether. אלא לרבנן, Ela l'Rabbanan, but according to
the רבנן Rabbanan that they say you have a קרבן במזיד korban
b'mezid with no warning, so then maybe even with warning קרבן נמי
מייתי korban nami maiti you could also bring a קרבן. korban. So
you’re right, there was a beautiful ברייתא braita that shows you get
lashes. Only problem is, it might be according to the opinion that
doesn’t believe that a מזיד mezid by שבועת פיקדון shvuat pikadon brings
a קרבן korban altogether. So that’s one way to get rid of
that ברייתא. braita.
Okay, now here’s another way. אמר ליה רב כהנא. Amar lei Rav
Kahana. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana said, okay, thank you. That was
a good way of answering that ברייתא braita and saying that we
haven’t proven the answer. But בר מן דהא, bar min d'ha, even
without that response of framing that ברייתא braita as ר' שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon,
דאנא תנינא לה. da'ana tanina lah. I know that ברייתא, braita, but
I have a very different version of that ברייתא. braita. So you
can’t bring a proof from that ברייתא. braita. אנא תנינא לה והכי
תנינא לה. Ana tanina lah v'hachi tanina lah. Here’s my version of
that ברייתא. braita. אחד זדונה ואחד שגגתה. Echad zedona v'echad shigagata. The
ברייתא braita says very different than your version of the ברייתא. braita.
My version of the ברייתא braita says whether מזיד mezid or שוגג
shogeg אשם בכסף שקלים. asham b'kesef shekalim. You bring an אשם. asham.
It’s very clear it’s only a קרבן. korban. So maybe that’s exactly
why I’m asking you the question, because I know there are two
versions of this ברייתא. braita. One version reads like you say, which
says that במזיד b'mezid you get lashes, and another version says במזיד
b'mezid you bring a קרבן. korban. So that’s exactly why I’m asking.
You can’t prove from this ברייתא, braita, there are two versions of
it. Now, with the version that במזיד b'mezid you bring a קרבן,
korban, how is this weightier than שבועת עדות? Shvuat Edot? Because the
context of the ברייתא braita is saying here’s how שבועת פיקדון Shvuat
Pikadon is weightier than שבועת עדות. Shvuat Edot. So ומאי חומרא, U'mai
chumra, so why is it weightier? Not because of lashes. But דאילו
התם חטאת בת דנקא. d'ilu hatam chatat bat danka. There it’s a
חטאת chatat and you can even if you get a real חטאת
chatat on the cheap even for like a few bucks, okay, והכא
אשם בכסף שקלים. v'hacha asham b'kesef shekalim. And here's an אשם asham
and it costs two שקל shekel which is a high minimum amount.
Also you could say that it's a fixed amount, I mean it's
always the קרבן korban of the animal. You don't have the option
of bringing a מנחה mincha or the birds if it is if
you're not as wealthy or if you're poor. Okay, so anyway, so
the weightiness here has nothing to do with lashes. The weightiness is
that it's always a fixed price minimum minimum amount. You know there's
a a high minimum is set for the cost and it's a
you know and it's always a that type of a קרבן. korban.
It is not a קרבן korban that what type of קרבן korban
you bring changes based on how wealthy or poor you are and
that the amount you pay for the קרבן korban does not have
a minimum set; here there is a minimum set. Okay, so that's
why I've got the question. We've got a you have because we
have one ברייתא braisa that says you get lashes that might answer
it. Maybe it doesn't answer it. Maybe that's רב שמעון Rav Shimon
who doesn't even have a קרבן korban in these cases. But even
without רב שמעון Rav Shimon we have another version of that ברייתא
braisa that says that you get חטאת, chatas, you bring the
and that you don't get lashes. So that's my question, what's the
הלכה? halacha? What's the story? Okay,
so דאביי d'Abaye says wait one minute. According to your version of
the ברייתא braisa וליגמור מינה, veligmor minah, let's with your text of
the ברייתא braisa let's learn the other way to answer the question,
that it's only a קרבן korban and it's not lashes according to
your version. So no, דילמא דלא אתרו ביה, dilma d'lo asru bei,
that you can't learn from my version of the ברייתא braisa because
my version of the ברייתא braisa might be talking without warning and
might be talking about a you know a מזיד meizid that he
wasn't warned that he would get lashes. So we don't have an
answer. Either we have ברייתות braisos contradicting or even within my version
of the ברייתא braisa we don't know what the הלכה halacha would
be with warning, maybe it's not talking with warning.
Okay, לשון אחר, lashon acher, here's a different version of how they
had that discussion. תא שמע, ta shema, אין חייבין על שגגתה ein
chayavin al shigagasa
מה הן חייבין על זדונה mah hein chayavin al zedona אשם בכסף
שקלים. asham bechesef shekalim. So you're not חייב chayav if you're a
pure שוגג. shogeg. What are you חייב chayav על זדונה? al zedona?
Because we you need an element of מזיד, meizid, you need to
willfully be lying. So it says an אשם. asham. מאי לאו דאתרו
ביה? mai lav d'asru bei? So this ברייתא braisa presumably is talking
about all cases when it says מזיד, meizid, presumably even if you
got lashes. So doesn't that seem to prove that even if it's
מזיד meizid it's a קרבן, korban, even with warning that you do
not get lashes? I'm sorry, I think I said that wrong a
minute ago. Anyway, it sounds like we're talking about all מזיד, meizid,
even with warning and saying that you don't get lashes, you get
a קרבן. korban. No, הכא נמי דלא אתרו ביה, hacha nami d'lo
asru bei, you can't prove it. Anything that says מזיד meizid you
bring the קרבן korban doesn't prove one way or the other because
it could be talking about that you did not get warned. Okay,
תא שמע, ta shema, come in here another ברייתא. braisa. Look, this
ברייתא braisa is comparing נזיר nazir to שבועת העדות. shvuas ha'edus. Now
רש״י Rashi says excuse me, שבועת הפיקדון. shvuas hapikadon. Now רש״י Rashi
says it's not clear what the context is. What we need, do
we need to compare a נזיר nazir to a case of a
שבועת הפיקדון? shvuas hapikadon?
But
תוספות Tosafos says that the context is we're trying to figure out
that when a נזיר nazir becomes טמא, tamei, the תורה Torah says
he brings a קרבן. korban. What would be the story if he
willfully became טמא? tamei? Would he get lashes and bring a קרבן
korban or only bring a קרבן korban or maybe get lashes and
not bring a קרבן? korban? So somewhat similar to the question we
have by שבועת הפיקדון. shvuas hapikadon. That's at least what תוספות Tosafos
says, he quotes the whole ספרא Sifra and says that that's the
context by the נזיר. nazir. But anyway, let's look at it. Okay,
תא שמע, ta shema, come in here.
Look, אם אמרת בנזיר טמא im amarta benazir tamei שכן לוקה, sheken
lokeh, if we say whatever we're saying by נזיר טמא nazir tamei
he gets lashes.
תאמר בשבועת הפיקדון tomar bishvuas hapikadon you can't assume that we're going
to say the same thing, whatever it is that we're saying, by
שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon
שאינו לוקה, she'eino lokeh, doesn't get lashes. So this is a classic
case of like you can't compare A and B because A is
weightier than B. So whatever הלכה halacha it is that you're saying
by A might not apply to B because B is less weighty.
So what weight is the A, the נזיר nazir weightier? You get
lashes as opposed to שבועת הפיקדון, shvuas hapikadon, it's not as weighty,
you don't get lashes. So presumably we're talking about the same scenario,
that he was warned. So and a נזיר nazir who's warned who
becomes טמא tamei gets lashes, and שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon warned doesn't
get lashes. Seems to be a straight answer to our question. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay, מדקאמר לוקה, mideka'amar lokeh, since the context is getting lashes for
the
נזיר, nazir, מדקאמר לוקה, mideka'amar lokeh,
I just lost my
place, מדקאמר לוקה mideka'amar lokeh מכלל דאתרו ביה, michlal d'asru bei, the
scenario is that he got warning. ותאמר בשבועת הפיקדון vesomar bishvuas hapikadon
and נזיר nazir is
being contrasted to שבועת הפיקדון shvuas hapikadon שאינו לוקה, she'eino lokeh, doesn't
get lashes, אבל קרבן מייתי, aval korban meisi, brings a קרבן. korban.
So there you go, seems to be a perfect example of perfect
clear statement that there's no lashes by שבועת הפיקדון. shvuas hapikadon. אמר
Amar says, no, מאי אינו לוקה? mai eino lokeh? דאינו נפטר במלקות.
de'eino niftar bemalkos. No, no, when it says he doesn't get מלקות
malkos by שבועת הפיקדון, shvuas hapikadon, it means מלקות malkos isn't enough.
He brings מלקות malkos and the קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara
says, wait a minute, מכלל ד michlal d נזיר טמא נפטר במלקות?
Nazir tamei niftar be-malkus?
So what, a נזיר Nazir telling me it's just מלקות malkus and
no קרבן? korban? Because you're saying a נזיר Nazir is מלקות, malkus,
this guy is not מלקות, malkus, which he just reinterpreted to mean
is not מלקות malkus alone, is מלקות malkus plus קרבן. korban. Which
by the way we should say reverses the point. Before we thought
it was saying נזיר Nazir is weightier and you can't apply it
to שבועת הפיקדון, Shevuas Hapikadon, שבועת הפיקדון Shevuas Hapikadon is less weighty.
Now we're saying the reverse. נזיר Nazir is lighter and you can't
apply something from שבועת הפיקדון Shevuas Hapikadon to נזיר Nazir because שבועת
הפיקדון Shevuas Hapikadon is weightier. Because נזיר Nazir only gets lashes and
שבועת הפיקדון Shevuas Hapikadon lashes does not suffice, it's lashes and a
קרבן. korban. So number one we just reversed the weight and the
order of the ברייתא, braisa, but fine. And we also have a
very big stretch. Not getting lashes means lashes is not enough. But
anyway, bracketing that, it says but what's the difference? נזיר Nazir is
both lashes and a קרבן korban also. הא קרבן כתיב. Ha korban
kesiv. It says explicitly that a נזיר טמא Nazir tamei brings a
קרבן. korban. So גמרא Gemara says no, התם דמייתי קרבן כי היכי
דתחול עליה נזירות דטהרה. Hasam de-maiti korban ki haychi de-seichul alei nezirus
de-tahara. There the קרבן korban is to get his new נזירות nezirus
to start. It's not part of his atonement. So anyway that still
is a basis for punishment slash atonement. A נזיר Nazir who became
טמא tamei willfully just gets מלקות, malkus, whereas שבועת הפיקדון Shevuas Hapikadon
could be according to this side of the argument מלקות malkus plus
a קרבן. korban. All right, so that's a way again of getting
out of it. But again all of the simple sense of all
these ברייתות braisos is that it is only a קרבן korban not
מלקות, malkus, although we did have one ברייתא braisa that was מלקות,
malkus, but the גמרא Gemara says that that could be רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who doesn't have a קרבן. korban. All right so now
the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבא. Amru rabanan kamei de-Rava. So remember these were
all rabbis from the בית מדרש Beis Medrash of רבא. Rava. So
they got a little bit of a discussion of what they were
learning outside the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. Then they came back to
the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and they said oh we were having
this whole discussion with רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, do you get lashes
or not lashes? We tried to bring a ברייתא braisa this way
or that way, we didn't come to a conclusion.
Okay so they said it all to רבא. Rava. So אמר להו
Amar lehu he said to them, מכלל דבחיובא עסקיתו בה אי איכא
עדים מיחייב מיחייב.
Miklal de-be-chiyuva askisu bah
ei ika edim mechayiv mechayiv.
So he basically said okay that's all very nice. I'm not really
interested in that or whatever, I know the answer to that or
I know that there's not a clear answer. But I'm more interested
now in exploring an implicit an assumption you were making that I
don't agree with. Why? Because your scenario had witnesses saying to the
guy don't lie, we know you've got that פיקדון. pikadon. If you
lie we'll be able to testify that you were lying. And then
the question was do you go ahead and and then the question
was do you go ahead and and get lashes or not? Okay
but but רבא Rava is saying...
hello...
yeah I can't take this right now I'm sorry... could you leave
a message please... okay I
apologize... I'm sorry
everybody...
all right... okay so where was I? I'm sorry. Okay so he
says look I don't think that there's a you're missing a point
here.
If there are witnesses that this guy is lying and your question
was does he bring מלקות? malkus? Does he get מלקות? malkus? Then
the then I don't get it. If they know he's got that
object in his pocket and that's how they could try to get
him to have to get מלקות, malkus, so then the...
so then
the... okay
if they know he's lying and through that they're going to try
to give him get מלקות, malkus, so then the question is why
is he חייב chayiv for denying altogether?
He's denying but his denial carry no weight carries no weight.
They can just testify in court that he has the object and
make him pay. So he said you have this whole discussion that
the witnesses know and they gave him warning and
and the question was will they be able to give him מלקות?
malkus? But what they know is they know he's lying and they
know he's got the object in his pocket. So he says I
don't think you have מלקות malkus or a קרבן korban in that
case because in that case his denial is not going to have
any consequence. We'll just testify that he's got the object. Okay and
now we get into a very interesting discussion which is if somebody
denies and I anyway can prove that he owes me the money,
is that going to be the קרבן korban of שבועת עדות? Shevuas
Eidut? So now we're on a completely different topic. Okay so he
says like this... where was he... אמר רבא. Amar Rava. So
אמר לו Amar lo he said back to them, מכלל דכי לא
אתרו ביה ואיכא עדים מחייב, m'chlal d'chi lo atru beih v'ika edim
mechayev, so you're assuming that without the warning but witnesses know he's
lying, they're taken for granted he would bring a קרבן. korban. I
don't agree with that assumption. כפירת דברים בעלמא הוא, kfirat devarim b'alma
hu, you know it's just כפירת דברים בעלמא kfirat devarim b'alma is
you're not being כופר ממון, kofer mamon, your denial does not have
the consequence of keeping money away from this guy because witnesses know
it and they'll be able to testify. Okay, and they're obviously kosher
witnesses because they could testify that you're lying for your discussion about
having glasses. So if there's kosher witnesses that you've got the object,
your denial is just words. You know, your only denial is words,
you are not actually denying a, you know, you know, you make
a claim and I say no, I don't have it, but you
didn't actually through that reject a debt of money. I mean, you
tried to, but it won't have the consequence of denying the person
money because there are witnesses. So he says, anyway I think this
whole case is moot because of the witnesses. כפירת דברים בעלמא הוא.
kfirat devarim b'alma hu.
Where were we? Ah, אלמא קסבר רבא, alma kasavar Rava,
so now we're going to focus on that idea. אלמא קסבר רבא,
alma kasavar Rava, from here we see that רבא Rava holds הכופר
בממון שיש עליו עדים, ha'kofer b'mamon she'yesh alav edim, if somebody denies
money that anyway I could prove is mine because I have witnesses,
פטור, patur, the guy's exempt from a קרבן. korban. And now we're
going to focus on that. אמר ליה רבי חנינא לרבא, amar leih
Rabbi Chanina l'Rava, so רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said to רבא, Rava,
תניא דמסייע לך, tanya d'mesayeya lach, I'll bring a ברייתא braita that
supports your position. וכחש בה, v'kichash bah, this is exactly by the
פסוקים psukim by the פקדון. pikadon. He denies it, פרט למודה לאחד
מן האחים או לאחד מן השותפין. prat l'modeh l'echad min ha'achim o
l'echad min ha'shutafim. So it's excluding the case where two brothers lent
you money
and you admit to one of them, yes, I admit to you
I owe you the money, but then the other brothers come and
I denied them, in that case you're going to be פטור. patur.
Well, unpack that in a minute. ונשבע על שקר v'nishba al sheker
and you swear falsely, פרט ללוה בשטר ולוה בעדים prat l'loveh b'shtar
v'loveh b'edim to exclude the case from there are witnesses or there's
a שטר shtar because presumably that's not a שקר, sheker, I mean
it is a שקר, sheker, but presumably a lie that can be
easily proven to be a lie doesn't have the same consequence. So
that seems to be exactly what you're saying. Something that easily could
be shown to be a lie because there are witnesses, there's evidence,
you're not חייב. chayav. Isn't that exactly what you're saying? אמר ליה,
amar leih, so רבא Rava said, אי משום הא לא תסייען, ei
mishum ha lo tesayeyan, if that's the only support you have for
me, that's not a real support. Why not? באומר לויתי ולא לויתי
בעדים לויתי ולא לויתי בשטר. b'omer loviti v'lo loviti b'edim loviti v'lo
loviti b'shtar. When it says you are denying a debt with witnesses
and a debt with a שטר, shtar, it's not describing the debt.
It's describing what you're denying. I say to you, you borrowed a
hundred dollars with me with a שטר shtar or you borrowed a
hundred dollars from me and there were witnesses,
and you say yes, I borrowed the hundred dollars but there was
no שטר, shtar, there were no witnesses. You're denying the שטר, shtar,
you're denying the witnesses, which is like, who the heck cares? You're
admitting the debt. But that's actually what it's going to say, that
the point of this ברייתא braita is to say that if the
denial is meaningless, it's not about something that was ever about the
money aspect of it, okay, then it is going to be exempt.
But that's not exactly the same, that's a real כפירת דברים. kfirat
devarim. We're not even talking about the debt, we're talking about whether
there were witnesses to the debt or whether there was a שטר
shtar to the debt and that's what you're denying. But if there's
a real denying of the debt, maybe if even if there are
witnesses who can prove it anyway, who knows, says רבא, Rava, that,
I mean, that's my contention, says רבא, Rava, is that you're exempt,
but this ברייתא braita isn't talking about that case. Okay, so let's
take a look. Okay, ממאי, mimai, how,
what makes me read the ברייתא braita in that way that doesn't
support me? מדקתני וכחש בה פרט למודה לאחד מן האחים או לאחד
מן השותפין
m'diktani v'kichash bah prat l'modeh l'echad min
ha'achim o l'echad min ha'shutafim
because the other thing we exclude is if you have denied it
to one of the brothers who, you know, if a group of
brothers entrusted something with you or one of the partners. האי אחד
מן האחים היכי דמי? hai echad min ha'achim heichi dami? What's the
scenario? אילימא דאודי ליה בפלגא דידיה, ilima d'odei leih b'palga dideih, let's
say two brothers lent you a hundred dollars, okay, so you said
to one brother, yes I admit to the fifty dollars I got
from you, and then to the other brother you say but I
deny the fifty dollars I owe you. So in that case איכא
כפירה דעיקר, ika kfira d'ikar,
so why should you be exempt from a שבועה? shvua? Then you
actually have are really denying the other brother the fifty dollars.
אלא לאו ela lav the case must be דאמרי ליה מתרווייהו יזפת,
d'amri leih mitravaihu yazafta,
they say to him, you borrowed from both of us a hundred
dollars. ואמר להו לא מחד מינייכו יזפי, v'amar lehu lo m'chad minaichu
yazafi,
no, I didn't borrow from both of you ראובן Reuven and שמעון,
Shimon, I only borrowed
from ראובן. Reuven. Okay, דהויא ליה כפירת דברים בעלמא, d'haveya leih kfirat
devarim b'alma, in that case you admit to the full debt, you're
just denying some irrelevant particular. It's not irrelevant to them because then
ראובן's Reuven going to pocket the money all to himself, but if
they as between themselves agreed that it was both of theirs, they'll
just split it. So therefore, in that's that's what's coming to exclude
to say you don't have a קרבן korban when what you're denying
is really immaterial. Okay? So that's a real כפירת דברים. kfirat devarim.
ומידי דרישא כפירת דברים סיפא נמי כפירת דברים umidi d'reisha kfirat devarim
seifa nami kfirat devarim and since that's the case in the beginning,
that's the case in the end, you're denying the existence of a
שטר, shtar, the existence... existence of עדים, edim, but
but you are not denying the debt itself. What happens if you
actually deny the debt itself but it could otherwise be proved through
שטר shtar or עדים? edim? That רבא Rava that we don't have
proof. רבא Rava says you're exempt, he calls that כפירת דברים kfeirat
devarim as well, but that we don't have proof for. Okay, תא
שמע, ta shma, come and hear: אינו חייב על שגגתה, eino chayav
al shigagtah, ומה הוא חייב? u'ma hu chayav? Oh
so you're not חייב chayav by a שוגג, shogeg, by a שבועת
הפיקדון, shvuat ha'pikadon, ומה הוא חייב על זדונה? u'ma hu chayav al
zdona? What are you חייב chayav by case of זדון? zadon? אשם
כסף שקלים. asham kesef shkalim.
Okay, fine. מאי לאו mai lav זדון עדים? zadon edim? Doesn't זדון
zadon mean even with witnesses? Of course that's such a funny question.
לא, lo, זדון עצמו. zadon atzmo. No, it's a מזיד meizid and
he knows it's a מזיד, meizid, we don't have witnesses to prove
it's a מזיד, meizid, but again, that's not a case where we
clearly have witnesses that know he's lying. תא שמע, ta shma, היו
שתי כיתי עדים. hayu shtei kitei edim.
There were two sets of witnesses. This is going back to שבועת
העדות, shvuat ha'eidus, you might remember that. כפרה ראשונה ואחר כך כפרה
שנייה שניהם חייבות. kafra rishona v'achar kach kafra shniya shneihem chayavot.
If one denied that they knew עדות eidus and then the other
one, they're both חייב. chayav. מפני שיכול אלו להשתלם בשניהם mipnei sheyachol
elu l'hishtalem bishneihem
because either group was sufficient. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
this is the same question it asked over there. בשלמא שנייה תתחייב
דהא כפרה לה ראשונה. bishlama shniya titchayev d'ha kafra lei rishona. I
get why the second group is חייב chayav because the first group
already denied, so the whole testimony, you know, was on their shoulders.
אלא ראשונה אמאי מחייבה? ela rishona amai michayva? But why is the
first group חייב chayav when they denied? There was already a second
one. הא קיימא שנייה, ha kayma shniya, the second one exists. So
the fact that they are חייב chayav sounds like that you're חייב
chayav even if it could otherwise be proved. Now, maybe there's a
slight difference by שבועת העדות shvuat ha'eidus and about the case of
a שבועת הפיקדון. shvuat ha'pikadon. By שבועת הפיקדון shvuat ha'pikadon there's still
a question that even though it could otherwise be proved, like we
have a relationship, you gave me something, I'm denying it, you know
there's a betrayal there and so on. You know, maybe the הלכות
halachot could be different, but let's assume
not and it's assuming that they are comparable. So if by שבועת
העדות shvuat ha'eidus it looks like you're חייב chayav even though it
is redundant, even though it could otherwise be proved, so here too
maybe it's חייב, chayav, it should presumably also be חייב chayav even
though it could otherwise be proved. הא קיימא שנייה? ha kayma shniya?
So אמר רבינא amar Ravina no, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan,
this is what the גמרא Gemara said before, it would be a
scenario where when the first group took the oath, the second group
actually could not testify at that moment. כגון שהייתה שנייה בשעת כפירה
ראשונה, k'gon she'hayta shniya b'sha'at kfira rishona, the second group when the
first one was taking her oath, קרובין בנשותיהם, kruvin binshoteihem, the two
witnesses of the second group were related through their wives, ונשותיהם גוססות,
u'nishoteihem gossot, and their wives were on their deathbed. Okay, מהו דתימא
רוב גוססין למיתה ma d'teima rov gossin l'mita and I might think
that I could treat it as if I'm already anticipating that they're
already going to be dead and therefore the first group is going
to be exempt because we can anticipate the second group can testify?
קמשמע לן kamashma lan that I don't say that. השתא מיהא חיי
נינהו ולא שכיבי. hashta miha chayei ninhu v'lo shchivi. Now they're alive
and they're not dead. So anyway, so that's the point over there,
but the way we get out of it is we say that
on the face of it, yes, it seems to say that you're
חייב chayav even though there are witnesses who otherwise could prove it.
If that's true by שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'eidus, presumably it's true by
שבועת הפיקדון. shvuat ha'pikadon. But our response is
that
that's a case where actually at the time the first group took
the oath, the second group was actually
invalid. But if there really was witnesses, maybe we would say you
would be exempt, it would be a כפירת דברים בעלמא. kfeirat devarim
b'alma. Okay, so we still don't have an answer. תא שמע, ta
shma, coming here: בעל הבית שטען טענת גנב בפיקדון. ba'al ha'bayis she'ta'an
ta'anat ganav b'pikadon.
Now,
a בעל הבית ba'al ha'bayis says where's my object that I entrusted
you? Now, until now what the guy is saying is you never
entrusted it to me. That's a שבועת הפיקדון. shvuat ha'pikadon. Also however
included in שבועת הפיקדון shvuat ha'pikadon is if the guy lies that
something happened to it that would exempt him from payment. Oh, it
was so terrible, some I was held up by these bandits at
gunpoint, etc., etc., and he's lied. That also would be this קרבן
korban of שבועת הפיקדון. shvuat ha'pikadon. Okay?
So let's say now if what he says happened is that it
was נגנב, nignav, burgled, people broke into my house and they stole
it in the middle of the night and it turns out that
he's lying. Not only does he have to pay it back and
bring the קרבן korban and so on, but because he claimed it
was נגנב nignav and had it been נגנב nignav the גנב ganav
would take take כפל, kefel, the interesting הלכה halacha is that in
that case he pays כפל kefel as well. Okay, but of course
the only way we're going to know that is if there were
witnesses that he was lying. So let's take a look. Okay? בעל
הבית שטען טענת גנב בפיקדון, ba'al ha'bayis she'ta'an ta'anat ganav b'pikadon, he
claims that it was burgled.
Okay? ונשבע והודה, v'nishba v'hoda, and he took an oath and then
he admits. ובאו עדים. u'ba'u edim. אם עד שלא באו עדים הודה,
im ad she'lo ba'u edim hoda, if he admitted before the witnesses
came. Okay, because remember this
כפל kefel is a קנס, knas, so it depends whether if he
admitted to it before the witnesses he won't pay. So
if he admitted before the witnesses came, משלם קרן וחומש. mishalem keren
v'chomesh. He doesn't pay כפל. kefel. He pays the principal and the
חומש, chomesh, and the fifth, that's what you take for שבועת הפיקדון,
shvuat hapikadon, okay? והאשם ve'ha'asham and the אשם. asham. אם משבאו עדים
הודה, im mishebau edim hoda, if he only admitted after the witnesses
came, so משלם תשלומי כפל ואשם meshaleim tashlumei kefel ve'asham he pays
double because he's treated the because again because he claimed the גנב
ganav he's treated like a גנב ganav and he pays double, so
that's a קנס knas but again if the witnesses beat him to
it he pays it, so he pays double. משלם תשלומי כפל ואשם
meshaleim tashlumei kefel ve'asham and he of course brings the אשם asham
because it's also the קרבן שבועת הפיקדון. korban shvuat hapikadon. He doesn't
also bring the חומש, chomesh, once you're paying double you don't also
pay the חומש. chomesh. Okay, so anyway the point is that witnesses
came! So witnesses came! So therefore he took an oath and there
were witnesses and he still is bringing the קרבן. korban. So this
is a clear proof against רבא. Raba.
הכא נמי כי דרבינא hacha nami kideravina no, this could also be
like רבינא Ravina meaning yeah maybe at the time he took the
oath the witnesses their wives were they were related to one another
through their wives etcetera etcetera you don't have to say their wives
were on their deathbed, okay? And later the witnesses the wives died
and then the witnesses were able to come and testify against him.
So you can't prove it. At the moment he took the oath
maybe the witnesses were not כשר, kasher, they became כשר kasher later.
Okay. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי amar lei Ravina leRav Ashi so
רבינא Ravina who provided the answer that let רבא Raba get out
of these proofs against him, so he now says the following to
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. תא שמע ta shema let's prove it from
this case. חמורה ממנה שבועת הפיקדון שחייבין על זדונה מכות ועל שגגתה
אשם בכסף שקלים. chamura mimena shvuat hapikadon shechayavin al zedona makot ve'al
shagagata asham bechesef shekalim. Going back to that ברייתא braita we quoted
earlier that says שבועת הפיקדון shvuat hapikadon is weightier than שבועת עדות
shvuat edut because if you're willful you get lashes, if you're מזיד
mezid you get lashes, and if you're שוגג shogeg you bring the
קרבן. korban.
So obviously we're talking about a parallel case that there are witnesses,
okay? די קאמר לוקה de'ka'amar loke since we're saying he gets lashes
מכלל דאיכא עדים michlal de'ika edim there are witnesses. וקאמר על שגגתה
אשם בכסף שקלים ve'ka'amar al shagagata asham bechesef shekalim and it says
that you bring a קרבן. korban.
So they're clearly cases of witnesses and if you do it, if
you are willful, meaning in both cases you know you're lying, let's
remember. But in one case you know you're bringing a קרבן korban
and you're willful and they gave you and they gave you warning
you get lashes. The other case is either they didn't give you
warning or you didn't think you didn't know you were חייב chayav
a קרבן korban whatever the case was, you're not going to get
lashes you'll bring a קרבן korban but there are still witnesses,
okay? And nevertheless you're bringing a קרבן. korban. אמר להו רב מרדכי
בר נינוא amar lehu Rav Mordechai bar Ninua no no no you
can't bring a proof from that ברייתא. braita. Remember why you can't
bring a proof from that ברייתא? braita? דאמר להו רב כהנא de'amar
lehu Rav Kahana because רב כהנא Rav Kahana had a different version
of that ברייתא. braita. אנא תנינא לה והכי תנינא לה ana tanina
la vehachi tanina la no no no I have that ברייתא braita
and I have a different version.
אחד זדונה ואחד שגגתה echad zedona ve'echad shagagata whether it's זדון zadon
or whether it's שוגג shogeg אשם בכסף שקלים asham bechesef shekalim both
ways it's a קרבן, korban, it does not have the scenario of
getting lashes and therefore we do not know from that ברייתא braita
that we're talking about with witnesses. תא שמע ta shema let's try
again. לא, אם אמרת בנזיר טמא lo im amarta benazir tamei this
will all sound very familiar. שכן לוקה תאמר בשבועת הפיקדון שאינו לוקה.
sheken loke tomar bishvuat hapikadon she'eino loke. So by a נזיר טמא
nazir tamei you get lashes, by שבועת הפיקדון shvuat hapikadon you don't.
So the only parallel case is is that there are witnesses in
both cases. היכי דמי heichi dami what's the case? אי דליכא עדים
אמאי לוקה ei deleika edim amai loke if there's no witnesses why
are you getting lashes in the נזיר nazir scenario? אלא דאיכא עדים
ela de'ika edim there are witnesses. וקתני תאמר בשבועת הפיקדון שאינו לוקה
vekatani tomar bishvuat hapikadon she'eino loke and it says that in the
parallel case by שבועת הפיקדון shvuat hapikadon you don't get you don't
get lashes. מכלל דלא לקי michlal dela laki you don't get lashes
אבל קרבן מייתי aval korban mayti you bring a קרבן korban and
remember the only other way we read that on the עמוד א
amud aleph was you don't only get lashes it's lashes and a
קרבן. korban. But one way or the other, okay, it is saying
that you bring a קרבן korban even with witnesses.
תיובתא דרבא תיובתא tiyuvta deRaba tiyuvta that is a complete contradiction of
רבא Raba so bet you didn't expect that that we're actually going
to come to a conclusion. So we have completely actually רבא Raba
didn't like this whole discussion about whether do you get lashes because
he said as soon as there are witnesses you're not going to
bring a קרבן korban you're not going to bring a קרבן korban
because your denial has no meaning and we have now shown that
רבא Raba is incorrect
that actually even if there are witnesses and even if you're not
going to get away with your denial your act of denial does
have meaning you do bring the קרבן. korban. Which of course then
goes back and makes us question שבועת עדות. shvuat edut. If there
are two sets of witnesses maybe we should also say there that
even the first set brings a קרבן korban because even if there
are other witnesses they're still denying. So we don't know the answer
to that by שבועת עדות shvuat edut but here we have completely
rejected רבא. Raba. Even with witnesses and even if we can prove
it otherwise your denial is going to bring you if you're denying
a real monetary debt you bring a קרבן. korban. Okay. So now
it says now we're going to have a more nuanced position than
רבא Raba which isn't contradicted by what we just said. רבי יוחנן
אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar הכופר בממון שיש עליו עדים חייב. hakofei bemamon
sheyeish alav edim chayav. If you deny a debt and there are
witnesses yes you're חייב chayav you just proved that from that whole
ברייתא braita about a נזיר. nazir. אבל בשטר aval bishtar but in
a document if you deny a debt that the guy has a
document against you פטור patur you're exempt. Why? You would think witnesses
are better than a document. So אמר רב פפא מאי טעמא דרבי
יוחנן amar Rav Pappa mai ta'ama deRabbi Yochanan no what's the reason
of רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? עדים, Edim, even though witnesses are like
eye-witnesses and they're seen as the best, but you know, they're always
a little bit more tenuous. עבידי דמייתי, avidi d'meisi, they could die,
they could go on a trip to China, you don't know what's
going to happen to them. שטר המונח, shtar hamunach,
but you know, if you have documentary evidence, and you got it
in your safe deposit box, okay, so that's, you're certain you're going
to be able to prove it. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
look, in principle I agree with רבא. Rava. If your denial is
meaningless then and because it's going to be proven anyway, then you're
exempt. The point though is is that witnesses is not seen as
meaningless because witnesses, they might not show up, they might be tripped
up, they might die, okay. A שטר, shtar, in the case of
a שטר, shtar, your denial is meaningless and you are going to
be exempt. So אמר ליה רב הונא, Amar lei Rav Huna, so
רב הונא Rav Huna said back, בריה דרבי יהושע לרב פפא, brei
d'Rabbi Yehoshua l'Rav Papa, שטר נמי עבידי דמירכס? shtar nami avidi d'mirkas?
Why do you think a שטר shtar is so definite? People lose
a שטר shtar as well. אלא אמר רב הונא בריה דרבי יהושע,
Ela amar Rav Huna brei d'Rabbi Yehoshua, היינו טעמא דרבי יוחנן. hainu
ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan. Here's the reason of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Not
because by a שטר shtar it's meaningless because he's definitely going to
prove it. No, forget that, here's the reason. משום דהוי שטר שעבוד
קרקעות, mishum d'havei shtar shibud karkaot, ואין מביאין קרבן על כפירת שעבוד
קרקעות, v'ein mevi'in korban al kfirat shibud karkaot, that
if there's a שטר shtar that means if I'm coming to you
and I say I have a, you owe me a hundred dollars
and I have a שטר shtar that says it, okay, so my
שטר shtar gives me right to collect, it leans on your land
and right to collect from your land. So when you're denying that
you owe it, you're denying a debt that has to do with
a debt of land because I'm claiming rights to your land. And
therefore because you're denying a debt to your land, a שבועה shvuah
on land is not a, you know, you don't bring a קרבן,
korban, there's not a consequence for taking a false שבועה shvuah on
land. שבועות Shvuot on land is a basic principle that they're excluded
from this category of, you know, שבועות shvuot and false oaths and
the consequence of the oath and so on, whether we even would
make the שבועה shvuah in the first place, okay.
ואין מביאין קרבן על כפירת שעבוד קרקעות. v'ein mevi'in korban al kfirat
shibud karkaot. איתמר, Itmar, so now we're going to get into, and
I guess we'll stop here, okay, because we are now going to
get into that debate. If somebody demands, you know, we had this
by שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut as well, come testify for me about
this debt that somebody owes me, this debt of land or he
stole my land. So if there's a שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut or
שבועת הפקדון shvuat hapikadon that involves land, is there going to bring
a קרבן korban or not? Actually let's just go like two more
minutes and get this started, so let's just get a little bit
more into this. איתמר, Itmar, so it was said and, alright, איתמר,
itmar, המשביע עדי קרקע, hamashbi'a edei karka,
so you have עדים edim who have testimony about land and they're
lying and they deny it and etc. is there a קרבן? korban?
פליגי רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Pligi Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Eleazar. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar debate. חד אמר חייב וחד
אמר פטור. Chad amar chayav v'chad amar patur.
One says חייב, chayav, one says פטור. patur. תסתיים דרבי יוחנן דאמר
פטור. Tistayem d'Rabbi Yochanan d'amar patur. Given what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said a minute ago about שטר, shtar, it must be רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is the one who says you're exempt here by שבועת
העדות shvuat ha'edut by land, okay. מדאמר רבי יוחנן הכופר ממון שיש
עליו עדים חייב, Mid'amar Rabbi Yochanan hakoper mamon sheyesh alav edim chayav,
if you deny money where there are witnesses you're חייב. chayav. שטר
פטור, Shtar patur, but if there's a שטר shtar you're exempt. And
the way we explained the difference was וכדרב הונא בריה דרבי יהושע,
uk'd'Rav Huna brei d'Rabbi Yehoshua, that because a שטר shtar includes means
that there's a debt of land and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
a שבועה shvuah relating to land you're exempt. So the same way
he says that by a שבועת הפקדון shvuat hapikadon he'll say it
by שבועת העדות. shvuat ha'edut. תסתיים, Tistayem, so that is a good
proof. Okay, so now we have said that that is therefore the
same debate, שבועת הפקדון, shvuat hapikadon, שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edut, is there
going to be a שבועה shvuah when land is involved? And that
is the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Eleazar. We will pick up with this tomorrow and see what the
debate is based on. Normally you should everybody should agree there's not
a שבועה shvuah about land, that tends to be a general agreement.
So what is the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Eleazar about whether in the case of שבועת הפקדון shvuat
hapikadon or שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut
if you take a שבועה shvuah that connects to land whether you're
going to be חייב chayav or not? Okay, we will end with
this for now.